A Guide to the Warren County (Va.) Court Records, 1832-1932
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Warren County (Va.) Court Records, 1832-1932
The Library of Virginia
1013617-1176238 circa
11.45 cu. ft. (16 boxes) and 14 v.
Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in a shipment of court papers from Warren County. A portion of the collection was transferred under accession number 37018.
Historical Information
Warren County was named for Joseph Warren, the revolutionary patriot who sent Paul Revere and William Dawes on their famous rides and who was killed at the Battle of Bunker Hill. The county was formed from Frederick and Shenandoah counties in 1836.
A Docket is a brief record of proceedings in a court of justice. It usually gives the style of the suit and the date the court first dealt with it. Sometime it gives the date the suit was removed from the docket.
An execution is a court order directing a sheriff or other officer to enforce a judgment, usually by seizing and selling the judgment debtor's property. An Execution Books lists executions sued out or pending in the sheriff's office. It shows notices of process, names of all parties, amount of judgment, date of execution, return date and sheriff's return.
A Writ is a written judicial order to perform a specified act, or giving authority to have it done. A written court order of a judicial process, directing that a sheriff or other judicial officer do what is commanded by the writ; or giving authority and commission to have it done. The Writ Docket is a book that have brief entries concerning writs that were enforced.
Fee Books are volumes showing the date of a duty performed by the clerk, the name of the person paying the fees, and the amount. It includes the fees charged attorneys, cash accounts, and the clerk's fees in common law and chancery cause.
A Memorandum Book is used for notations of entries to be made in other books.
Judgments are civil cases in which justice was administered on the strictly formulated rules of common law. The majority of cases in this record series relate to matters of debt.
Scope and Content
Warren County (Va.) Court Records, 1832-1932 contains Executions for the County, Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery and Circuit Courts; Justice of the Peace Records; Magistrates and Chancery Execution;, Writ Docket; Minutes; Process Book A; Chancery Rules Books; Common Law Execution A; Order of Attendance; Register of Descriptive Lists of Persons Convicted of a Felony; Fee Books; Fee Book and Memorandum Book; Common Law Papers; Judgments; and Commonwealth Causes.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Warren County Court Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm"
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court
Subjects:
Circuit courts--Virginia; Court records--Virginia--Warren County
Geographical Names:
Warren County (Va.)--History
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records--Virginia--Warren County; Judicial records--Virginia--Warren County; Public records--Virginia--Warren County
Contents List
- Executions, 1843-1853
  Box 235 contains Executions, 1843-1853.
- County Court Executions, 1853-1859
  Box 239 contains Executions, 1853-1859.
- Executions, 1842-1883
  Barcode Number 1013627 contains Executions, 1842-1883 is in Box 237. Barcode Number 1013628 contains Executions, 1843-1877 is in Box 236. Part of the executions were from cases heard in the Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery and the Circuit Court.
- Executions, 1832-1892
  Box 243 contains Executions Returned by Constables, 1872-1892; Magistrates' Executions, 1832-1856; and Chancery Executions, 1839-1892.
- Writ Docket, 1850-1903
  This book contains records of writs heard in the County Court and Superior Court of Law and Chancery.
- Minutes, 1844-1870
  This book contains the clerk's rough notes of court proceedings that were later transcribed into an order book.
- Process Book A, 1836-1894
  This book shows how the court exercised jurisdiction over a person or a specific property.
- Chancery Rule Book A, 1836-1879
  Rule was a session of the Court. Chancery Causes were first heard in Rules before they were heard in the Chancery Court. These rules were for Chancery Causes heard in the Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery.
- Chancery Rule A, 1837-1913
  Rule was a session of the Court. Chancery Causes were first heard in the Rules before they were heard in the Chancery Court. These rules were for Chancery Causes heard in the County Court and Circuit Court.
- Chancery Executions A, 1839-1894
  This book contains executions issued by the Chancery Court.
- Common Law Executions A, 1836-1883
  This book contains executions issued by the Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery and the Circuit Court.
- Orders of Attendance, 1837-1884
  This book contains the names of the witness called to appear at court for judgments, criminal cases, and or chancery causes.
- Register of Descriptive Lists of Persons Convicted of Felony, 1867-1932
  This books gives specific physical characteristics that can be used to identity the felons.
- Fee Books, 1836-1883
  Barcode Number 1096505 contains Fee Book, 1836-1853. Barcode Number 1096504 contains Fee Book,1854-1875. Barcode Number 1096506 contains Fee Book, 1868-1871. Barcode Number 1096502 contains Fee Book, 1881-1883. Barcode Number 1096503 contains a combination Fee Book and Memorandum Book for the years 1869-1882.
- Common Law Papers, 1836-1921 (bulk 1849-1921)
  Barcode Number 1134427 contains Common Law Papers, 1836-1846, Box 1. Barcode Number 1134334 contains Common Law Papers, 1849-1858, Box 2. Barcode Number 1134335 contains Common Law Papers, 1858-1874, Box 3. Barcode Number 1134336 contains Common Law Papers, 1875-1885, Box 4. Barcode Number 1134337 contains Common Law Papers, 1886-1897, Box 5. Barcode Number 1134338 contains Common Law Papers, 1896-1909, Box 6. Barcode Number 1134339 contains Common Law Papers, 1907-1913, Box 7. Barcode Number 1134340 contains Common Law Papers, 1913-1918, Box 8. Barcode Number 1134341 contains Common Law Papers, 1917-1921, Box 9. These records are Accession Number 37018.
- Judgments and Commonwealth Causes, 1836-1910
  Box 2 contains Judgments, 1880-1910 and Commonwealth Causes, 1836-1910.
- Judgment, 1840-1879
  Box 1 contains Judgments, 1840-1879.